Michele Tufano

Ph.D.



Research Interests

My research interests include the application of Deep Learning techniques to Software Engineering tasks such as Automated Program Repair, Software Testing, Maintenance and Evolution. I also worked on Android Testing, Mining Software Repositories, Code Quality, and Software Building.

I currently work in the Natural Language Understanding team in Microsoft Bing.

Experience

2019-Present Software Engineer, Microsoft, Redmond, WA, USA.

Natural Language Understanding & Experience Team

2016–2019 **Research Assistant**, *The College of William and Mary*, Williamsburg, VA, USA. W&M Advised by Prof. Denys Poshyvanyk

2018–2018 Research Intern, Microsoft Research, Redmond, WA, USA.

Advised by Kim Herzig and Hitesh Sajnani

2014–2016 **Teaching Assistant**, The College of William and Mary, Williamsburg, VA, USA.

o CS 421 - Database Systems

CS 141 - Computational Problem Solving

Education

2014–2019 Ph.D. in Computer Science, The College of William and Mary,

Williamsburg, VA, USA. (GPA: 3.75).

Dissertation: Learning Code Transformations via Neural Machine Translation

2012–2014 Master in Computer Science, University of Salerno, Fisciano, Italy.

 $110/110~\mathrm{cum}$ laude

2008–2012 Bachelor in Computer Science, *University of Salerno*, Fisciano, Italy.

110/110 cum laude

Master thesis

Title An Empirical Study on Developer Related Factors Characterizing Fix-Inducing Commits

Supervisors Andrea De Lucia, Gabriele Bavota, Rocco Oliveto

Languages

Spoken Italian (mother tongue), English (expert)

Programming Java (expert), Python, R, Matlab, JavaScript, SQL (good)

Google Scholar

Citations https://scholar.google.com/citations?user=KmeqxSEAAAAJ&hl=en

Awards

- 2019 W&M William & Mary Award for Excellence in the Natural & Computational Sciences
- 2018 ICPC **Best ERA Paper Award**, at the 26th IEEE/ACM International Conference on Program Comprehension (ICPC), "Towards Just-In-Time Refactoring Recommenders".
- 2015 ICSE **ACM SIGSOFT Distinguished Paper Award**, at the 37th IEEE/ACM International Conference on Software Engineering (ICSE), "When and Why Your Code Starts to Smell Bad".

Journal Articles

- 2019 [J6] Z. Chen, S. Kommrusch, **M. Tufano**, L.-N. Pouchet, D. Poshyvanyk, M. Monperrus, "SEQUENCER: Sequence-to-Sequence Learning for End-to-End Program Repair", IEEE Transactions on Software Engineering (TSE 2019).
- 2019 [J5] **M. Tufano**, C. Watson, G. Bavota, M. Di Penta, M. White, D. Poshyvanyk, "An Empirical Investigation into Learning Bug-Fixing Patches in the Wild via Neural Machine Translation", ACM Transactions on Software Engineering and Methodology (TOSEM 2019).
- 2017 [J4] M. Linares-Vásquez, C. Vendome, **M. Tufano**, and D. Poshyvanyk, "How Developers Micro-Optimize Android Apps", Journal of Systems and Software (JSS 2017).
- 2017 [J3] M. Tufano, F. Palomba, G. Bavota, R. Oliveto, M. Di Penta, A. De Lucia, and D. Poshyvanyk, "When and Why Your Code Starts to Smell Bad (and Whether the Smells Go Away)", IEEE Transactions on Software Engineering (TSE 2017).
- 2016 [J2] M. Tufano, F. Palomba, G. Bavota, M. Di Penta, R. Oliveto, A. De Lucia, and D. Poshyvanyk, "There and Back Again: Can you Compile that Snapshot?", Journal of Software: Evolution and Process (JSEP 2016).
- 2016 [J1] **M. Tufano**, G. Bavota, D. Poshyvanyk, M. Di Penta, R. Oliveto, and A. De Lucia, "An Empirical Study on Developer Related Factors Characterizing Fix-Inducing Commits", Journal of Software: Evolution and Process (JSEP 2016).

Conference Publications

- 2019 [C15] M. Tufano, C. Watson, G. Bavota, M. Di Penta, M. White, D. Poshyvanyk, "Learning How to Mutate Source Code from Bug-Fixes", In Proceedings of the 35th IEEE International Conference on Software Maintenance and Evolution (ICSME 2019) Cleveland, OH, USA, 2019, 12 pages. (23% acceptance rate).
- 2019 [C14] M. Tufano, J. Pantiuchina, C. Watson, G. Bavota, D. Poshyvanyk, "On Learning Meaningful Code Changes via Neural Machine Translation", In Proceedings 41st ACM/IEEE International Conference on Software Engineering (ICSE 2019) Montréal, QC, Canada, May 25-31, 2019, to appear 12 pages. (21% acceptance rate)
- 2019 [C13] M. Tufano, H. Sajnani, K. Herzig, "Towards Predicting the Impact of Software Changes on Building Activities", In Proceedings 41st ACM/IEEE International Conference on Software Engineering (ICSE 2019), New Ideas and Emerging Results - Montréal, QC, Canada, May 25-31, 2019, to appear 4 pages. (31% acceptance rate)
- 2019 [C12] C. Bernal-Cárdenas, K. Moran, M. Tufano, Z. Liu, L. Nan, Z. Shi, and D. Poshyvanyk, "Guigle: A GUI Search Engine for Android Apps", In Proceedings 41st ACM/IEEE International Conference on Software Engineering (ICSE 2019), Formal Research Tool Demonstration Montréal, QC, Canada, May 25-31, 2019, to appear 4 pages. (47% acceptance rate)
- 2019 [C11] M. White, M. Tufano, M. Martinez, M. Monperrus, and D. Poshyvanyk, "Sorting and Transforming Program Repair Ingredients via Deep Learning Code Similarities", In Proceedings 26th IEEE International Conference on Software Analysis, Evolution and Reengineering (SANER 2019) angzhou, China, February 24-27, 2019, to appear 12 pages. (27% acceptance rate)

- 2018 [C10] M. Tufano, C. Watson, G. Bavota, M. Di Penta, M. White, D. Poshyvanyk, "An Empirical Investigation into Learning Bug-Fixing Patches in the Wild via Neural Machine Translation", In Proceedings of the 33rd IEEE/ACM International Conference on Automated Software Engineering (ASE 2018) Montpellier, France, 2018, 6 pages. (21% acceptance rate).
- 2018 [C9] M. Tufano, C. Watson, G. Bavota, M. Di Penta, M. White, D. Poshyvanyk, "Deep Learning Similarities from Different Representations of Source Code", In Proceedings of the 15th IEEE/ACM International Conference on Mining Software Repositories (MSR 2018) Gothenburg, Sweden, 2018, 12 pages. (33% acceptance rate).
- 2018 [C8] J. Pantiuchina, G. Bavota, M. Tufano, D. Poshyvanyk, "Towards Just-In-Time Refactoring Recommenders", In Proceedings of the 26th IEEE/ACM International Conference on Program Comprehension (ICPC 2018), Early Research Achievement Track - Gothenburg, Sweden, 2018, 4 pages. (47.8% acceptance rate).
- 2017 [C7] K. Moran, M. Tufano, C. Bernal-Cardenas, M. Linares-Vasquez, G. Bavota, C. Vendome, M. Di Penta, D. Poshyvanyk, "MDroid+: A Mutation Testing Framework for Android", In Proceedings of the 40th IEEE/ACM International Conference on Software Engineering (ICSE 2018) Research Demonstrations Track Gothenburg, Sweden, 2018, 4 pages. (35% acceptance rate).
- 2017 [C6] M. Linares-Vasquez, G. Bavota, M. Tufano, K. Moran, M. Di Penta, C. Vendome, C. Bernal-Cardenas, D. Poshyvanyk, "Enabling Mutation Testing for Android Apps", In Proceedings of 11th Joint Meeting of the European Software Engineering Conference and the 22nd ACM SIGSOFT Symposium on the Foundations of Software Engineering (ESEC/FSE 2017) Paderborn, Germany, 2017, 12 pages. (24% acceptance rate).
- 2016 [C5] M. White, M. Tufano, C. Vendome, and D. Poshyvanyk, "Deep Learning Code Fragments for Code Clone Detection", In Proceedings of the International Conference on Automated Software Engineering (ASE 2016) Singapore, 2016, 12 pages (19% acceptance rate).
- 2016 [C4] M. Tufano, F. Palomba, G. Bavota, R. Oliveto, M. Di Penta, A. De Lucia, and D. Poshyvanyk, "An Empirical Investigation into the Nature of Test Smells", In Proceedings of the International Conference on Automated Software Engineering (ASE 2016) Singapore, 2016, 12 pages (19% acceptance rate).
- 2015 [C3] F. Palomba, D. Di Nucci, M. Tufano, G. Bavota, R. Oliveto, D. Poshyvanyk, A. De Lucia, "Landfill: an Open Dataset of Code Smells with Public Evaluation", In Proceedings of the 12th IEEE/ACM Working Conference on Mining Software Repositories (MSR 2015) Florence, Italy, 2015, 4 pages.
- 2015 [C2] M. Tufano, F. Palomba, G. Bavota, R. Oliveto, M. Di Penta, A. De Lucia, and D. Poshyvanyk, "When and Why Your Code Starts to Smell Bad", In Proceedings of the 37th International Conference on Software Engineering (ICSE 2015), Florence, Italy, 2015, 12 pages (18.5% acceptance rate).
- 2015 [C1] F. Palomba, M. Tufano, G. Bavota, R. Oliveto, A. Marcus, D. Poshyvanyk, and A. De Lucia, "Extract Package Refactoring in ARIES", In Proceedings of the 37th International Conference on Software Engineering (ICSE 2015) Demonstrations Track, Florence, Italy, 2015, 4 pages (59% acceptance rate).

Full list of publications, data, tools, and source code available at: https://tufanomichele.com